Guide to the Ford Madox Ford collection, [ca. 1850]-1973
Ford, Ford Madox collection,
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Ford Madox Ford collection, [ca. 1850]-1973 (bulk 1850-1939).
4605
Ford Madox Ford 1873-1939.
37.8 linear ft.
Correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, broadsides, bound manuscripts, photographs, and clippings.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, broadsides, bound manuscripts, photographs, and clippings, mainly spanning the period from the maturity of Ford's grandfather, Pre-Raphaelite painter Ford Madox Brown, to the death of Ford himself. Material from Ford's career ranges from unpublished novels and short stories of the 1890's and early 1900's to journal articles, literary reviews, lectures, addresses, and radio talks he wrote or delivered in the last 20 years of his life, including complete manuscripts of many published and unpublished novels, nonfiction books, stories, poems, plays, essays, and musical compositions.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
English novelist and influential editor of literary journals; also biographer, art critic, and poet. Born Ford Madox Hueffer; changed last name to Ford in 1919.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Correspondence, manuscripts, typescripts, broadsides, bound manuscripts, photographs, and clippings, mainly spanning the period from the maturity of Ford's grandfather, Pre-Raphaelite painter Ford Madox Brown, to the death of Ford himself. Material from Ford's career ranges from unpublished novels and short stories of the 1890's and early 1900's to journal articles, literary reviews, lectures, addresses, and radio talks he wrote or delivered in the last 20 years of his life, including complete manuscripts of many published and unpublished novels, nonfiction books, stories, poems, plays, essays, and musical compositions. Included are the manuscript of "Seraphina," the basis of the novel Romance which Ford wrote with Joseph Conrad; manuscripts of Ford's novels The Fifth Queen, The Privy Seal, The Heart of the Country, The Young Lovell, and Women and Men; a complete version and a "printer's copy" of The Good Soldier; manuscripts of a number of Ford's nonfiction works, including his biography of Ford Madox Brown; and some issues of the literary magazines he edited, the English Review and the Transatlantic Review. The collection also contains galley proofs (9 leaves) with James Joyce's corrections of his Work in Progress, a fragment of Finnegan's Wake that appeared in the Transatlantic Review.
Also included are postcards from Ford depicting scenes from Germany before World War I; letters and articles documenting Ford's increasing concern about Nazi expansionism, and his efforts to help Jewish refugees, in the 1930's; Arthur Mizener's manuscript material and correspondence for his biography of Ford, The Saddest Story; and David Dow Harvey's manuscripts for his bibliography of Ford.
Correspondence includes Ford's letters to his wife Elsie Martindale, daughters Katharine Hueffer Lamb and Julia Madox Loewe, and lovers Violet Hunt and Stella Bowen; Ford's army correspondence notebook from World War I, and letters to Joseph Conrad from the front; and much additional correspondence with Conrad and other writers, literary agents, and publishers. Correspondents include, in addition to those named above, Henry James, H.G. Wells, Ezra Pound, Jean Stafford, W.H. Auden, Gertrude Stein, Allen Tate, Theodore Dreiser, T.S. Eliot, John Ruskin, Ford Madox Brown, and publishers including Greenslet, Gollancz, Munson, Lippincott, and Allen and Unwin. Also included is correspondence of Ford's biographer Arthur Mizener with Janice Biala, Rebecca West, Eudora Welty, Katherine Anne Porter, and others.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ford, Ford Madox,1873-1939.; Auden, W. H.(Wystan Hugh), 1907-1973.; Bowen, Stella.; Brown, Ford Madox, 1821-1893.; Conrad, Joseph, 1857-1924.; Dreiser, Theodore, 1871-1945.; Eliot, T. S.(Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965.; Harvey, David Dow.; Hueffer, Elsie Martindale.; Hueffer, Katharine Lamb.; Hunt, Violet, 1862-1942.; James, Henry, 1843-1916.; Joyce, James, 1882-1941.; Loewe, Julia Madox.; Mizener, Arthur.; Mizener, Arthur.; Munson.; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980.; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972.; Ruskin, John, 1819-1900.; Stafford, Jean, 1915-; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946.; Tate, Allen, 1899-; Wells, H. G.(Herbert George), 1866-1946.; Welty, Eudora, 1909-; West, Rebecca, 1892-; George Allen & Unwin.; Greenslet.; J.B. Lippincott Company.; Victor Gollancz Ltd.
Titles:
English review.; Transatlantic review.
Subjects:
English literature--20th century.; English fiction--20th century.; Modernism (Literature).; Authors and publishers--England.; Publishers and publishing--England.; Authors, English--Relations with women.; Pre-Raphaelites--England.; Refugees, Jewish.; World War, 1914-1918--Personal narratives.
Places:
England--Intellectual life--20th century.; Great Britain--Armed Forces--History.
Form and Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Portraits.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
Organized into the following series: Manuscripts by Ford; Ford memorabilia and documents; letters from Ford; manuscripts and correspondence of others; photographs; bound manuscripts by Ford; clippings; Stella Bowen papers.
Manuscripts arranged alphabetically by title; Ford's letters, alphabetically by recipient; others' manuscripts and letters, alphabetically by author; photographs, alphabetically by subject or (when subject is unknown) photographer; clippings, in chronological order.
Bound manuscripts are listed at the bottom of this guide but cataloged separately.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Ford Madox Ford manuscripts
A
B-D
E-G
H-J
K-M
N-P
Q-R
S-T
U-Z, Fordiana, Memorabilia, Documents
Series II. Outgoing correspondence
A-B
Stella Bowen
C-J
Elsie Martindale Hueffer
K-L
M-P
Q-Z
Series III. Incoming correspondence and manuscripts
A-B
Janice Biala
Stella Bowen
William A. Bradley
C
D
E-F
G
H
David Dow Harvey - Ford Madox Ford bibliography
Hunts (excluding Violet)
Violet Hunt
I-L
M
Arthur Mizener
N-O
P-R
S-Z
Series IV. Photographs
A-F
Forf Madox Ford
G-Q
R-Z
Photograph Album
Link to the guide containing descriptions of the individual photos within the album. PDF File
Series V. Clippings of Ford and Stella Bowen
Series VI. Literary Portraits
Series VII. The Saddest Story facsimile
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Ford Madox Ford manuscripts
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - A
    - AM: "A solis ortus cardine", Sept.4, 1916; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Poem, written in the trenches during WWI in a battle along the Somme River.
    - AMS Account book of funds in the London and County Banking Co., Ltd., 1901-1906; 60 leaves (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Accounts Oct. 1, 1901-Jan. 24, 1906, in monogrammed pigskin notebook.
    - AMS Account book of funds in the London City and Midland Bank, Ltd., 1906-1907; 28 leaves (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Accounts Jan. 1, 1906-Apr. 2, 1907, in monogrammed pigskin notebook.
    - AMS Account book of funds in the London City & Midland Bank, Ltd., 1908-1909; 20 leaves (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Accounts Apr. 30, 1908-Jan. 11, 1909, in monogrammed pigskin notebooks.
    - AMS Account book of funds in the London City & Midland Bank, Ltd, 1909-1910; 72 leaves (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Accounts Jan. 18, 1909-June 14, 1910, in brown leather notebook.
    - AMS Account book of funds with Messrs. Barclay & Co., Ltd., 1910-1915; 43 leaves (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Accounts Aug. 8, 1910-Aug. 19, 1915, in brown leather notebook.
    - TM "Adeline and Oscar", [1939?]; 18 leaves (Box 1, Folder 7)
      [Fragment, draft]Written in New York, a possible early version or variant of "Memories of Oscar Wilde". (Harvey D412)
    - TM "Adversity' and "Birthday -song", [1891-1893?]; 1 leaf (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Written in London, two poems written under pseudonym "Fenil Haig".
    - AM "Albade", [Summer, 1930]; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Not the "Albade" of the "Poems Written on Active Service". Written in Ballancourt, which the poem references twice, and dates from the beginning of Ford's liaison with Janice Biala.
    - TM "The Alcestis of Euripides" freely adapted for the modern stage., Mar. 1919; 79 leaves (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Two versions; complete manuscript in paper wrapper, 52 leaves, and alternate adaption of the last half, 27 leaves. Commissioned by Nigel Playfair, but unpublished. (Harvey Cv[5])
    - TM "The American Scene", [[193-?]; 8 leaves, carbon (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Possibly written in New York, this apparently unpublished manuscript contains a witty comparison of the New York and London literary scenes.
    - TM "And even in Paradise devised ...", [192-?-193-?]; 4 leaves+1 leaf graph paper (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Possibly written in New York, a "play" in which the names of the characters and snippets of dialogue are to be found by referencing a crossword puzzle at the top of the page. The dramatic personae are all characters from Old Testament mythology (Adam, Lillith, Satan). With some corrections.
    - AM "And [of] halved angels with golden wings ...", [1890-1894?]; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Fragment of two drafts of a short poem, written on the reverse side of a copy of "April Weather" by Mathilde Blind, in the hand of Ford.
    - "Arms and the mind", Dec. 1980; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Printed facsimile of Ford's work of 1916 under the nom de plume "Miles Ignotus" and originally entitled "A Day of Battle", this essay is here published for the first time by "Esquire", v. 94, no.6, Dec. 1980, pp. 78-80.
    - Army correspondence notebook., Aug.-Sept. 1916; 50 leaves (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Cardboard covered army issue notebook containing Ford's records of the regimental mess of which he was in charge, carbons of letter to his Commanding Officer and to C.F.G. Masterman. Also a carbon of the poem "Clair de lune" which was published in "On Heaven and Other Poems," 1918.
    - TM [Article on the young American mid-western writers], [n.d.]; 1 leaf (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Carbon fragment, third page of a draft of an article or book on the subject of the crop of American writers coming out of the mid-west, specifically Chicago. With some corrections.
    - TM [Article on wine], [n.d.]; 3 leaves (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Carbon fragment of pages 9-11 of one of Ford's many articles on wine. Probably one of the first articles which was published. With some corrections.
    - AM "As a wounded hart ..."], July 23, 1892; 7 leaves (Box 2, Folder 10)
      An early meditation on youthful love and a description of a summer excursion with the then Elsie Martindale. A 16 line poem is on the last page: "On Taplow lock the sun shines down ..."
    - TM "As Thy Day", [1934]; 331 leaves (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Title when published became "Henry for Hugh". A few holograph corrections.
    - TM "At the Caveau Roughe", [1931-1936]; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Draft. Title variant: "L'Interprete - au Caveau Rouge." Includes original and carbon copy of poem, with variant versions of subsection "Sonnet de Ronssard" and "Plaisir d'Amour." See Harvey A76 for notes on the textual changes occurring between this poem's publication in the 1931 "New English Poems" and as the V poem in "Buckshee" of the 1936 "Collected Poems."
    - A & TM "At the Fairing", [pre-1904]; 3 leaves (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Poem. Three versions: 2 typescript, one of which is titled "The Humble Chapman cries his wares at a Fairing" a third in Ford's hand. Apparently unpublished.
    - TM "The Athens of the South", [1937-1938?]; 10 leaves (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Carbon copy of article on Nashville, Tenn. Identified by a note in Janice Biala's hand as having been published in "Vogue"; not in Harvey.
    - TM [Autobiographical entry for inclusion in Georges Schrieber's "Portraits and Self Portraits"], [1936]; 2 leaves (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Carbon copy of a brief and witty summation of the author's life; written in Paris.
    - TM [Autobiographical information], [193-?]; 3 leaves (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Carbon copy of draft [?] of a summary of Ford's literary life, written in the third-person. Includes references to Ford Madox Brown and Joseph Conrad as well as the publication history and reception of the author's writings.
    - TM [Autocriticism concerning "The Rash Act"], [1933]; 4 leaves (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Draft of an article by Ford commenting upon his novel "The Rash Act", with holograph corrections in the author's hand. Published in "Week-end Review", Sept. 9, 1933.
    - TM "Auto-plagiarism", [after 1927]; 11 leaves (Box 2, Folder 17.5)
      An article, detailing a minor scandal concerning two works by Conrad: "The Sisters, and Unfinished Story" and "The Arrow of Gold". Includes a synopsis of "The English Novel" for Lippincott's "The One Hour Series", which was published in 1929, and a list of books of collected poems by Ford.
    - A & TM "Autumn", [1894-1896]; 3 leaves (Box 2, Folder 18)
      A musical composition, the lyrics of which are typed in full on the first page.
  - B-D
    - AM ["Bodurdoe and Gunter"], [1891-1895]; 39 leaves (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Fragment. Possibly written in London, short story or part of a novel, probably unpublished. Not found in Harvey.
    - AM "Books for Exchange II", [after 1899]; 3 leaves (Box 3, Folder 2)
      Fragment [?] of short essays on Turgenev's [Turgeniev] "Sportsman's sketches".
    - [Book on travel and authors}, [n.d.]; 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Beginning pages of book. Dedication (to Olivia Shakespeare) and Table of Contents I Ch. II - Italy, Ch. IV - J.M. Whistler, Ch. VII - Burne Jones, Ch. IX - D.M. Rossetti) of an unpublished book.
    - TM "Buckshee", [1931?]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Fragment. Poem I. ("Aitchka") of the "Buckshee" sequence.
    - TM "Cambridge on the Caboodle", [after 1927]; 9 leaves (Box 3, Folder 4.1)
      Carbon of a review of E.M. Forster's "Aspects of the Novel", with revisions apparently in Ford's hand.
    - TM "The Case of Elizabeth Canning", [n.d.]; 32 leaves (Box 3, Folder 4.2)
      Written in Sussex, a retelling of an important eighteenth-century court case. The particulars of the story are taken from "The Trial of Elizabeth Canning, Spinster for Wilful & Corrupt Perjury...Monday the 29th of April to Wednesday the 8th of May 1754" from "The 1766 Edition of State Trials". With revisions in Ford's hand.
    - AM "The Castle in Spain", [n.d.]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Poem, which appeared in different forms as "Castles in the Fog" in the "Daily Mail Books suppl.", Jan. 19, 1907, and as "Finchley Road" in "Songs from London", 1910. Harvey Ciii (4a)
    - TM [Champetre] "Aichka Apificata, [1931-1936]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 6)
      Draft of variant text of Poem VI of the "Buckshee" sequence.
    - TM "Children's Song", [1901-1904?]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Incomplete poem. Harvey CIII (3)k; published in "The Face of Night"
    - AMS "Chinese Music", [1894-1896]; 16 leaves (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Written in Kent, two versions of an essay on Chinese music, one in Ford's hand (7 leaves), and one in Elsie Martindale Hueffer's hand (12 leaves + folder) Apparently unpublished.
    - TM "Citizen or Subject", [n.d.]; 12 leaves + folder (Box 3, Folder 8.3)
      Article on American and British notions of citizenry and justice. Enclosed in a folder from the Article Department, Brandt & Brandt, New York, and with revisions apparently in Ford's hand.
    - TM "Citizen or subject: Why I shall never become an American citizen", [[1927?]; 3 leaves (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Carbon of an incomplete typescript, possibly a variant of Ford's published article of the same title.
    - Clippings concerning personal life, [1924?-1927?]; 6 leaves (Box 3, Folder 10)
      Press clippings from the "Chicago Tribune" 91924, 1927), the "New York Herald" (1926, the "New York World" (192-?), and another unspecified New York publication (1930?) concerning Ford.
    - AM ["Club Night"], [n.d.]; 2 leaves (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Poem, which appeared in a slightly different form in "Songs from London", 1910.
    - AM/TM "Coda", [1931?]; 13 leaves (Box 3, Folder 12)
      Fragments and drafts of "Coda" from the "Buckshee" sequence. Page 23 is written on verso of TLS to Ford from Theodor Bosanquet [?] ("Time and Tide"), April 14, 1936.
    - TM "Coda", [1931-1936]; 14 leaves (Box 3, Folder 13)
      Fragments and drafts of "Coda" of the "Buckshee" sequence.
    - TM "Coda", [1936?]; 7 leaves (Box 3, Folder 14)
      Clean typescript of the text as published.
    - "Collected Poems" galley proofs, 1936; 109 leaves (Box 3, Folder 15)
      Printed proofs of Ford's "Collected Poems", published by Oxford University Press, New York.
    - TM "The Colonel's Shoes", [after 1917?]; 16 leaves (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Carbon of the short story. Title page marked: The Northern Newspaper Syndicate, Kendal. No. ""U" 29 Short Story.
    - "The Colonel's Shoes" news clipping., [Jan. 11, 1920?]; 1 leaf + 2 photocopies (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Newspaper clipping of short story. Published in "Reynold's Illustrated Newspaper"
    - TM {Compagnie Transatlantique] "Anitchka Anadyomene", [1931-1936?]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 18)
      Variant text of Poem II of the "Buckshee" sequence.
    - AMS "Conceits", [1893]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 19)
      Poem, later published in "The Questions at the Well", part II, in 1893. Signed with Ford's initials.
    - TM "Creative History and Historical Sense", [after 1903]; 20 leaves (Box 3, Folder 19.5)
      Apparently unpublished article on critical debate sparked by A.F. Pollard's book "Henry VIII". Includes references to Professor Goldwin Smith's review of the book. With revisions by Ford.
    - AMS ["Critique of a writing by Miss Black"], [1894?-1900?]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 20)
      Fragment of a critique of a book by Miss Black.
    - AM "The Dark Forest. Part II", [1911?]; 173 leaves (Box 3, Folder 21)
      Written perhaps in collaboration with Violet Hunt, the manuscript is a part of the later published "The New Humpty-Dumpty", 1912. It is mostly writtne in unidentified hand and some pages are typed. Pages 192-205 are in Hunt's hand, and pages 205-206 are in Ford's. The exterior folder has "Ford Madox Hueffer, 17th February, 1911, Geissen" written on it. Title page of manuscript reads: "in the property of F. B. Pinker, Talbot House, Arundel Street, London W.C." Harvey Civ (5)
    - AM "A Day of Battle", Sept. 15, 1916; 11 leaves (Box 3, Folder 22)
      Perhaps meant to be part of a larger work, the sub-heading includes the numeral I and the subtitle "Arms and the Mind". Top right corner of title page scribed: "Written on the Ypres Salient: 15th Sep., 1916". Signature at the bottom of the last page reads "Miles Ignotus". See also Ford's essay "War--the Mind."
    - TM "Death with Dishonour", Sept. 9, 1938; 9 leaves (Box 3, Folder 23)
      Fragment draft recording Ford's reaction to the Munich conference, especially the role of Britain. With holographic changes; unpublished.
    - AM "Death with Dishonour", Aug. 30, 1908; 3 leaves (Box 3, Folder 24)
      Earlier fragment draft of Ford's thoughts about the Munich conference.
    - TM "Demigods", [n.d.]; 6 leaves (Box 3, Folder 24.5)
      Original title "Beau Sabreur" crossed out and new title penciled in, this document is a synopsis of Ford's novel "A Little Less than Gods", written in 1928.
    - AM/TM ["Destiny's Role Given Koehler"], [Jan. 1935]; 4 leaves (Box 3, Folder 25)
      Report from the Hauptmann-Lindbergh kidnapping trial, later published in the "New York World-Telegram" on January 20, 1935.
    - TM ["Dinner with Turbot"] "The Pensive Epicurean", [1939]; 22 leaves (Box 3, Folder 26)
      Later published in "Vogue", September 15, 1939, the original title is "The Pensive Epicurean". Some holograph corrections made to draft, with a page of dictated copy by hand of Janice Biala.
    - TM & AM [Draft of chain letter...peace...sketch], [193-?]; 5 leaves (Box 3, Folder 27)
      Carbon drafts of a chain letter intended as a protest against the effect of war on "intellectual workers," with an accompanying sketch signed by Ford.
    - AMS "The Dream Hunt", [n.d.]; 1 leaf (Box 3, Folder 28)
      A slightly different version of the poem which later appeared in "Songs from London", 1910, with a fragment from another poem at the bottom of the page.
  - E-G
    - AM ["Edith], [1890-1894?]; 5 leaves (Box 4, Folder 1)
      Fragments of 2 chapters of a novel: chapter 1 with the epigraph "Quein se casa por amores/ Ha de vivir con dolores." Chapter II with, "Er war ein alter Konig/ Sein Herz war schwer, sein Haupt war grau." Perhpas from "The Shifting of the Fire."
    - AM Eight untitled poems, [n.d.]; 13 leaves (Box 4, Folder 2)
      Fragments of early poems; some with corrections and some with several versions; probably none published.
    - AMS "Elspeth", May 1891; 30 leaves (55 numbered pages) (Box 4, Folder 3)
      Short story in 4 chapters, probably unpublished.
    - TM "The English Novel; Author's apology to Hugh Walpole", [Jan. 1930]; 5 leaves (Box 4, Folder 4)
      Dedicatory letter to Hugh Walpole, acknowledging his role in Ford's decision to publish "The English Novel". With Ford's corrections.
    - TM "Enigma", [1920-1923]; 11 leaves with folder (Box 4, Folder 5)
      Unpublished manuscript of a short story with a few corrections. Title page on "Coopers-Bedham-Fittleworth-Sussex" stationary, which according to Harvey, would date the manuscript between 1920 and 1923.
    - TM [Ford's entry for Who's Who in Literature], [1921?]; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 6)
      Entry form of the Literary Year Book Press.
    - TM "Epilogue", [n.d.]; 11 leaves (Box 4, Folder 6.1)
      Two versions of manuscript about WWI, one 8 pages; the other 3 pages.
    - TM "The Escape: a One Act Drama", [n.d.]; 8 leaves (Box 4, Folder 6.2)
      A single act drama, concerning a married couple and infidelity.
    - TMS"Every Man: a Sequence", [n.d.]; 6 leaves (Box 4, Folder 7)
      Two versions of a poem: 4 leaves of typescript, and 2 leaves of holograph comprising four of the typed poems in another form. Appears in "Songs from London", 1910.
    - TM "The Exile", [n.d.]; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 8)
      Poem, published with minor differences in "High Germany", 1912.
    - TM [On Ezra Pound-Canto IX], [1932]; 3 leaves (Box 4, Folder 9)
      A draft of Ford's chapter in "Ezra Pound: Some Testimonials by Ernest Hemingway, Ford Madox Ford, T.S. Eliot, Hugh Walpole, Archibald MacLeish, James Joyce and Others". With holograph additions and corrections.
    - AM "Faith and Hope, Being part of a double-Trilogy in Park & Parlour, [1890-1893]; 15 leaves (Box 4, Folder 10)
      Fragment of poem, includes I (1) Faith in the Park; I (2) Faith in the Parlour; II (1) Hope in the Park. Published in "The Questions at the Well", 1893.
    - TM "The Feather", [n.d.]; 1 leaf (Box 4, Folder 11)
      Poem, published with slight differences in "High Germany", 1912.
    - TM "Felo de Se", [pre-1904]; 3 leaves (Box 4, Folder 12)
      Poem, another version of "The Ballad of a Suicide"; unpublished in this form.
    - AM & TM "The Fifth Queen", Part I-II, [1904?]; 400 leaves (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Holograph and typewritten versions, with corrections, of the first two parts of Ford's novel, which was published in 1906. Ford's address on the title page of the hand written version of Part II dates at least that part as 1904.
    - AM "The Fifth Queen", Part III, [1904?]; 68 leaves (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Third part of Ford's novel, with corrections.
    - AM "The Fifth Queen Shewn", [1904-06?]; 159 leaves (Box 7, Folder 3)
      Complete holograph manuscript, parts I, II, III of Ford's novel, later published under the title "Privy Seal" in 1907.
    - AM "First Lecture", [after 1924]; 6 leaves (Box 4, Folder 13)